Phillip: When providing information to customers
it is not only good to know what you are talking
about, but you should also be aware of the
different rules associated with that information.
There are three categories of
rule you need to follow, these are
Legal, Organizational, and Ethical.
These rules are put in place to protect
customers by making sure the information
they’re given is accurate and not misleading.
• Maddy: Legal rules are rules you’re required
to follow by law, and if you don’t follow
these you may be liable to criminal penalties
like fines or even a prison sentence.
• Organisational rules are the rules your
organization requires you to follow.
They’re set by the organization, and although
you might not be breaking the law, by not
following them, you could face disciplinary
proceedings, or even the sack if you don’t.
• Ethical rules are rules that aren’t in
law or enforced by your organization, but
which are still the right thing to do.
Phillip: It is also important to note
that sometimes the same rule will be a
legal, organizational, and ethical all
at once, whereas other might only fall
into one or two of these categories.
So, let’s look at some examples of the
rules that may relate to your role.
Maddy: Legal
It’s against the law to deliberately give
false or misleading information to a customer.
For example, if you’re selling a health
product and make wild claims and exaggerations
about what it can do, like claiming it can
cure serious illnesses, but you know that
it can’t, then you’re committing fraud.
This is a criminal offence, and the
consequences can be severe, especially
if people are hurt as a result.
There are also laws about the type of
information that you can share with a
customer, such as personal or sensitive
information about another customer or
colleague which might be legally protected.
Phillip: Organisational rules
Organisational rules often cover things
like maintaining discipline and promoting a
particular kind of culture in the workplace.
For example, if you worked as part of
the team in a retail environment, there’s
probably a dress code you must follow.
This is important to maintain the integrity of
the brand, as you are the face of the business.
When providing information to customers,
the organization might require its people
to use a particular style and tone of voice.
This is usually to try and enhance
their reputation and make their product
or service seem more attractive.
For example, they might require their people to
make sure they mention certain features about
a product or service, early in the conversation
with a customer to try and get their attention.
Or there might be a rule that you should mention
other products or services, that complement
the one the customer is interested in.
Organisational rules will also require their
people to follow all the legal rules associated
with their role in the organisation too.
Maddy: Ethical rules
There are ways of communicating information
with customers which are legal, permitted by
organizational rules, but are not always ethical.
For example, you might encourage a
customer to believe that a particular
product or service is very popular.
This can be done by just providing smaller bits
of information, so they form a particular picture,
like mentioning you’ve recently had to order
more stock of a product as it is selling out.
This might be true, but you could be presenting
it to the customer in such a way, to make
them think that this product is popular and
in high demand, which might not be the case.
You may even get commission
for the amount you sell.
So, this isn’t technically lying, and you’re not
making false claims about the product or service,
but it is still deceitful and isn’t ethical.
Likewise, using highly charged emotional
language in a negotiation, or expressing
exaggerated sadness, if it looks like the
customer is walking away, isn’t illegal and
might not be breaking any organizational
rules, but it isn’t very ethical, because
you’re manipulating the customers emotions.
Phillip: By making sure you follow all legal,
organizational, and ethical rules, you help to
encourage a more open, honest, and safe working
environment for your team and for customers.
It’s especially important to remember
that breaching these rules, can also put
customers safety in jeopardy, and there
can be severe consequences for this.